Register of the Alexander Dallin Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alexander Dallin Papers
1928-2000
79093
Hoover Institution Archives
361 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 envelope, 1 microfilm reel (153.5 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, orders, interview transcripts, notes, and printed matter, relating to the German occupation of areas of the Soviet Union during World War II, the Vlasov movement, and Soviet collaborators and partisans. Includes photocopies of German military documents. Used in preparation of the book by A. Dallin, German Rule in Russia, 1941-1945 (London, 1957). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Dallin, Alexander
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
1924, May 21 Born, Berlin, Germany
1947 B.S., College of the City of New York
1953 Ph.D., Columbia University
1956-1969 Professor of International Relations, Columbia University
1957 Author, German Rule in Russia, 1941-1945
1962 Author, The Soviet Union at the United Nations
1965 Author, The Soviet Union and Disarmament
1970 Co-Author, Political Terror in Communist Systems
1971-1978 Senior Research Fellow, Hoover Institution, Stanford University
1971- Professor of History and Political Science, Stanford University
Russkai͡a osvoboditelʹnai͡a armii͡a.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--German occupation, 1941-1944.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945--Collaborationists.; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  See photo card catalog.
- Subject file, 1933-1972
  Autobiography, bibliography, clippings essay, identification, instructions, interviews, leaflets, letters, lists of names, maps, memoirs, memoranda, minutes, orders, printed matter, proposals, questionnaires, radio bulletins, radio message, reports, resolutions, speeches, statistics, studies, summaries of discussions and conferences.
  - General. Bibliography -- Central and Eastern Europe (in Armenian, Azerbaijani, Belorussian, Chuvash, English, Estonian, Georgian, German, Kalmyk, Latvian, Lithuanian, Russian, Tatar, and Ukrainian), 1938-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baltic Peoples (Estonians, Latvians, Lithuanians) -- Relations with Nazis. Clippings, letter, memorandum, report (in English and German), 1940-1945 (Folder 2)
  - Cossacks
    - General. Notes, printed matter (in English and Russian), 1941-1951 (Folder 3)
    - Collaboration with Nazis. Excerpt from letter, memoranda, order, study (in English, German, and Russian), circa 1943-1951 (Folder 4)
    - Cossacks in U.S. Report (in Russian), 1950, undated (Folder 5)
  - Dzhugashvili, Iakov. Clipping (in Russian), 1940 (Folder 6)
  - Germany
    - Anti-Nazi Propaganda. Leaflet (in German), undated (Folder 7)
    - Conference on Political and Social Problems of Europe, 19-21 June 1943. Summary of reports (in German) (Folder 8)
    - Nazi Government. Letter of Hermann Goering to Hitler (in German), 1945 (Folder 9)
    - Nazi View on World War II
      - Memorandum -- Joseph Goebbels (in German), 1943 (Folder 10)
      - Printed matter -- Alfred Rosenberg (in German), 1943 (Folder 11)
  - Harvard University Refugee Interview Project
    - Analysis of Respondents, circa 1951 (Folder 12)
    - Interviews, 1950-1951 (Folder 13-16)
    - Questionnaires, undated (Folder 17)
    - Studies -- plans and titles, undated (Folder 18)
  - Nikolaevski, B. I. -- Memorial Volume. Letters, 1966-1972 (Folder 19)
  - Russia
    - Foreign Policy. Excerpts from memoranda, letter, printed matter (in English, German, and Russian), 1939-1951 (Folder 20)
    - Intelligence Service
      - General. Clippings, list of agents (in Russian and Ukrainian), 1951-1954 (Folder 21)
      - Rote Kapelle. Printed matter (in French), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Internal Policy
      - General. Interviews, printed matter, report (in English and Russian), 1943-1956 (Folder 2)
      - Concentration Camps
        - Camp for Repatriants near Poltava. Clipping (in Russian), 1949 (Folder 3)
        - Camps in Siberia. Letters (in Russian), 1936-1937 (Folder 4)
      - Prison in Dubno. Report (in German), 1941 (Folder 5)
      - Secret Police. Interview, printed matter, report (in English, German, and Russian), 1942-1955 (Folder 6)
    - Nationality Question -- Historical Reviews
      - Belorussians. Mimeographed issuances (in Belorussian), 1952-1953 (Folder 7)
      - Chechen and Ingush. Study (in Russian), circa 1950 (Folder 8)
      - Crimean Peoples. Essay (in German), undated (Folder 9)
      - Crimean Tatars. Clippings (in Ukrainian), 1951 (Folder 10)
      - Kalmyks. Clippings (in Russian), 1949 (Folder 11)
      - Non-Russian Peoples of Ural-Volga Region. Map, study (in Russian), 1933 (Folder 12)
    - Nazi Policy and Conduct
      - General
        - Interviews -- German Respondents, 1951 (Folder 13)
        - Interviews -- Russian Respondents, 1950-1951 (Folder 14)
        - Letters (in English, German, and Russian), 1944-1957 (Folder 15)
        - Memoirs (in German and Russian), undated (Folder 16)
        - Memoranda (in German), 1941-1944 (Folder 17)
        - Notes, undated (Folder 18)
        - Printed matter (in German and Russian), 1941-1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Reports (in German), 1941-1943 (Folder 2)
        - Statistics, 1939 (Folder 3)
        - Studies (in English and German), 1951 (Folder 4-6)
        - Summary of Meeting with Hitler (in German), 1945 (Folder 7)
      - Agencies
        - General. Letter, maps, reports, summary of meeting with Alfred Rosenberg (in German), 1941-1944 (Folder 8)
        - Breslau Eastern European Institute. Report (in German), 1948 (Folder 9)
        - Economic Staff East. Memoranda, minutes, reports (in German), 1941-1944 (Folder 10)
        - Economic Staff East -- Subagencies. Maps, memoranda, reports (in German), 1941-1943 (Folder 11)
        - High Command of German Army. Report (in German), 1941 (Folder 12)
        - High Command of German Army -- Subagencies. Reports (in German), 1941-1944 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - Reich Ministry for the Occupied Eastern Territories
          - General. Interviews, letters, map, memoranda, reports (in English and German), 1941-1954 (Folder 2)
          - Subagencies
            - Reich Commissariat Ostland. Memorandum, printed matter, report, speech (in Belorussian and German), 1942-1943 (Folder 3)
            - Reich Commissariat Ukraine. Letter, list of local offices, reports (in German), 1942-1944 (Folder 4)
        - Reich SS Leader. Security Police and Security Service. List of officials, reports (in German), 1942-1945 (Folder 5)
      - Agriculture
        - General
          - Instruction (in German), 1941 (Folder 6)
          - Interviews -- German Respondents, 1951 (Folder 7)
          - Interviews -- Russian Respondents, 1950-1951 (Folder 8)
          - Letters (in German), 1953-1955 (Folder 9)
          - Memoranda (in German), 1941-1942 (Folder 10)
          - Notes, undated (Folder 11)
          - Printed matter (in German and Russian), 1942-1943 (Folder 12)
          - Reports (in English and German), 1942-1943 (Folder 13)
        - Agencies
          - Economic Staff East -- Subagencies. Reports (in German), 1942-1944 (Folder 14)
          - Reich Ministry for the Occupied Eastern Territories. Report (in German), 1943 (Folder 15)
        - Belorussia. Interviews, 1950-1951 (Folder 16)
        - Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic. Interviews, memorandum, report (in English and German), 1942-1951 (Folder 17)
      - Agriculture and Trade -- Ukraine
        - Interviews, 1950-1951 (Folder 18)
        - Memoranda (in German), 1942-1944 (Folder 19)
        - Printed matter -- clippings (in German), 1943 (Folder 20)
        - Reports (in German), 1941-1955 (Folder 21)
      - Church. Appeals, clippings, interviews, letters, notes, reports (in English, German, Russian, and Ukrainian), 1941-1954 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Collaboration
        - General. Interviews, letters, memoir, printed matter, report, study (in Azerbaijani (?), English, German, and Russian), circa 1942-1951 (Folder 2)
        - Kaminski Brigade
          - General. Interviews, map, notes, printed matter, study (in English, Russian, and Ukrainian), 1942-1969 (Folder 3)
          - Lepel. Letter, memorandum, report, summary of discussion (in German), 1943-1944 (Folder 4)
          - Lokot
            - Letters (in German and Russian), 1942-1956 (Folder 5)
            - Orders (in German), 1942-1944 (Folder 6)
            - Proposals (in German), 1943 (Folder 7)
            - Reports (in German), 1942-1944 (Folder 8)
          - Russian Nazi Party. Letters, manifestos, memoir, notes, order, report (in English, German, and Russian), 1944-1951 (Folder 9)
          - Voskoboinikov, K. P. -- Russian Popular Socialist Party. Manifesto, report (in English and Russian), 1941-1942 (Folder 10)
        - Military
          - General
            - Instructions (in German), 1941-1944 (Folder 11)
            - Interviews, 1950-1951 (Folder 12)
            - Letter (in Russian), 1952 (Folder 13)
            - Memoirs (in German and Russian), undated (Folder 14)
            - Memoranda (in German), 1943 (Folder 15)
            - Printed matter, 1943 (Folder 16)
            - Reports (in English and German), 1941-1944 (Folder 17)
            - Statistics (in German), 1944 (Folder 18)
            - Studies (in French and German), 1951 (Box 6, Folder 1)
            - Summary of meeting (in German), 1944 (Folder 2)
          - Belorussians. Memoir, notes (in English and Russian), circa 1948 (Folder 3)
          - Peoples of Caucasus Region
            - General. Orders (in German), 1944-1945 (Folder 4)
            - Azerbaijans. Report (in Russian), 1951 (Folder 5)
            - Georgians. Interview, memorandum, (in English and German), 1943-1951 (Folder 6)
            - Kabardians. Note, undated (Folder 7)
          - Russian Popular National Army. Memoir, circa 1951 (Folder 8)
          - Volga Tatars. Excerpts from book, 1951 (Folder 9)
        - Native Governments and Organizations
          - General. Interviews, memoranda, reports, studies (in English, German, and Russian), circa 1942-1951 (Folder 10)
          - Azerbaijan National Committee. Notes, summary of discussion, undated (Folder 11)
          - Belorussia. Autobiography, clipping, list of collaborators, memoir, minutes, notes (in Belorussian, English, German, and Russian), 1943-1953 (Folder 12)
          - Crimean Tatars -- National Central Committee. Identification, orders (in German), 1945 (Folder 13)
          - Kabardino-Balkaria. Memoir (in Russian), undated (Folder 14)
          - Non-Russian Peoples of Ural-Volga Region -- Conference, March 1944. Resolutions, speech (in German) (Folder 15)
          - Oriol Province. Interview, proposal (in English and German), circa 1943-1951 (Folder 16)
          - Turkestan National Committee. Summary of discussion, 1951 (Folder 17)
        - Vlasov Movement
          - General
            - Interviews, 1951-1952 (Folder 18)
            - Letters (in German and Russian), 1951-1953 (Folder 19)
            - Memoirs (in German), 1949 (Folder 20)
            - Memoranda (in English, German, and Russian), 1943-1945 (Folder 21)
            - Printed matter -- clippings (in German and Russian), 1950-1952 (Folder 22)
            - Radio message by Soviet Government (in German), 1942 (Folder 23)
            - Reports (in German), 1942-1944 (Folder 24)
            - Summaries of discussions (in German), 1945 (Folder 25)
          - Leadership. Interviews, notes, printed matter, 1950 (Folder 26)
          - Nationality Question. Letters, memoranda, printed matter, reports (in German), 1944-1945 (Folder 27)
          - Propaganda. Clippings, instruction, leaflet, notes, report (in English, German, and Russian), 1942-1944 (Folder 28)
        - See also (Russia -- Nationality Question -- Chechen and Ingush/Crimean Tatars) and (Russia -- Nazi Policy and Conduct -- Nationality Question -- Ukrainians)
      - Demographic Impact. Study, undated (Folder 29)
      - "Lessons of History" -- Projection to Future. Notes, study, undated (Folder 30)
      - Nationality Question (Box 7)
        - General. Clippings, interviews, letters, memoranda, notes, study, summary of conference (in English and German), 1951-1953 (Folder 1)
        - Belorussians. Notes, reports (in English and German), circa 1943-1951 (Folder 2)
        - Jews and Gypsies. Clippings, interviews, study (in English and Russian), 1943-1951 (Folder 3)
        - Peoples of Caucasus Region. Instructions, order (in German), 1941 (Folder 4)
        - Ukrainians
          - Instruction (in German), 1941 (Folder 5)
          - Interviews, 1950-1951 (Folder 6)
          - Letter (in German), 1939 (Folder 7)
          - Memoranda (in English and German), 1942-1944 (Folder 8)
          - Notes, undated (Folder 9)
          - Printed matter (in French, German, and Ukrainian), 1942-1950 (Folder 10)
          - Radio script (in Russian), 1944 (Folder 11)
          - Resolutions and Decisions -- Conferences of Separatists (in Ukrainian), 1942-1943 (Folder 12)
          - Statistics, circa 1943 (Folder 13)
          - Studies (in English and German), undated (Folder 14)
          - Summary of meeting with Hitler (in German), 1941 (Folder 15)
      - Ostarbeiters and Prisoners of War. Instruction, interviews, notes, speech, study (in English, German, and Russian), circa 1943-1951 (Folder 16)
      - Propaganda (Folder 17)
        - General. Leaflets, memorandum, report, study (in English, German, and Russian), 1942-1951
        - Agencies
          - General. Letter, summary of conference (in German), 1943-1944 (Folder 18)
          - Reich Ministry for the Occupied Eastern Territories. Letters, notes, summary of meeting (in English and German), 1942-1943 (Folder 19)
          - Reich Ministry for Popular Enlightenment and Propaganda. Letters, radio bulletins, reports (in German and Russian), 1943-1944 (Folder 20)
          - Russian Press. Clippings, study (in Russian), 1942-1951 (Folder 21)
      - Urban Population
        - General. Map, statistics, study, undated (Folder 22)
        - Belorussia. Report (in German), 1942 (Folder 23)
        - Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic. Report, summary of conference (in German), 1942 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Ukraine. Interviews, memoirs, printed matter, report (in English, German, Russian, and Ukrainian), 1941-1952 (Folder 2)
    - Nazis and Bolsheviks -- Comparison
      - General
        - Interviews, 1950-1951 (Folder 3)
        - Printed matter -- clippings (in German and Russian), 1943-1949 (Folder 4)
        - Reports (in German), 1942-1944 (Folder 5)
        - Studies, circa 1951 (Folder 6)
      - Peasants. Interviews, studies, 1950-1951 (Folder 7)
    - Partisans -- Guerrilla War
      - Resistance to both Bolsheviks and Nazis. Memoirs (in Russian), undated (Folder 8)
      - Resistance to Nazis
        - General
          - Interviews, 1950-1951 (Folder 9)
          - Leaflets (in German and Russian), 1943-1944 (Folder 10)
          - Letters (in English and Russian), 1943-1953 (Folder 11)
          - Memoranda (in German), 1942 (Folder 12)
          - Printed matter (in Russian), undated (Folder 13)
          - Reports (in German and Russian), 1942-1951 (Folder 14)
          - Studies, undated (Folder 15)
        - Belorussia. Leaflets, memoirs, reports (in German and Russian), circa 1942-1951 (Folder 16)
        - Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic. Leaflet, report (in German), 1942 (Folder 17)
    - Rumanian Occupation. Memoir, report (in German and Russian), circa 1941-1951 (Folder 18)
  - Totalitarianism. Notes, undated (Folder 19)
  - Ukrainians outside of Russia. Memorandum, printed matter (in German and Ukrainian), 1939-1952 (Folder 20)
  - U.S. Intelligence -- Gehlen Organization. Clipping, 1955 (Folder 21)
  - White Emigres
    - General. Interview, note, printed matter (in English and Russian), 1950 (Folder 22)
    - Relations with Nazis. Letters, notes, reports (in English and German), circa 1940-1951 (Folder 23)
- Incremental materials (Box 9-363)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1956
  - 2018 release of declassified records, 1956 (Reading room workstation)